If you’re anything like me,
you have lots of ambitious
plans for the future.
I’ve got a whole series of
new books I want to write,
thousands more
videos to script.
But guess what?
None of us may be able to do
any of the things we want to do
if we don't have our health.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we hear about new research
on Alzehimer's from Dr. Dean Ornish.
And we share the results of the
first randomized controlled trial
investigating whether a plant-
based diet and lifestyle program
may reverse the course of
early-stage Alzheimer’s disease.
Dr. Dean Ornish was
the first to show,
in a randomized
controlled trial,
that a plant-based diet
and lifestyle program
could apparently reverse
the progression
of our number one killer,
heart disease.
Opening up arteries without
drugs, without surgery.
Then, he showed the same
plant-based program
could potentially
reverse the course
of early-stage
prostate cancer
and also elongate
telomeres,
suggesting an anti-
aging effect as well.
But when he told me
he was going to see
if he could reverse the progression
of Alzheimer's disease,
Surely, he was biting off a little
more than he could chew.
Dementia is the most
feared condition of later life.
There’s a common
misconception
that we have no control
over whether we
develop dementia,
but the good news is
that although Alzheimer’s
may be incurable,
at least it is preventable.
There is an emerging consensus
that “what’s good for our hearts
is also good for our heads,”
because clogging of the
arteries inside the brain
with atherosclerotic plaque
is thought to play a role
in the development of
Alzheimer’s dementia.
Too much cholesterol
in our blood
is unanimously recognized
to be a risk factor
for the development
of Alzheimer’s disease.
Those with a total cholesterol
of 225 mg/dL or more
may have nearly
25 times the odds
of ending up with amyloid
plaques in their brain
10 to 15 years later.
After all, what is the
Alzheimer’s gene, APOE?
It codes for the major cholesterol
carrier inside the brain.
This may explain the
so-called Nigerian paradox:
They have among the highest
rates of the Alzheimer’s gene
but some of the lowest
rates of Alzheimer’s disease.
How is that possible?
Genes load the gun,
but lifestyle pulls the trigger.
The paradox may be explained
by their low cholesterol levels,
probably due to their
diets low in animal fat.
So, in terms of dietary guidelines
for the prevention of Alzheimer’s,
we should center our
diets around vegetables,
legumes, fruits,
and whole grains.
In other words, the dietary
pillar of lifestyle medicine:
whole food,
plant-based nutrition.
Or, if that’s too complicated,
"plants, plants, and more plants."
That may help explain
why vegetarians
may be up to three times less likely
to become demented later in life.
But it’s not all-or-nothing.
Even just substituting 5%
of animal protein with plant protein
appears to significantly reduce
the risk of dying from dementia.
But prevention isn’t sexy.
When prevention works,
nothing happens,
but the same diet and lifestyle
that helps prevent heart disease
was proven to
help reverse it.
Until then, it was believed
that heart disease progression
could only be slowed,
not stopped or reversed,
similar to how Alzheimer’s
disease is viewed today.
So, what if you put
people with Alzheimer’s
on the same plant-
based program?
You don’t know until
you put it to the test.
A randomized,
controlled,
phase 2 clinical trial
to see if the progression
of Alzheimer’s disease
may be slowed, stopped,
or perhaps even reversed.
They randomized about
50 men and women
diagnosed with early-
stage Alzheimer’s
to either make no lifestyle
changes for 20 weeks
or eat a whole food,
plant-based diet
(with supplements
like vitamin B12),
moderate exercise
(like walking half
an hour a day),
stress management
(like relaxing with
breathing exercises),
and getting group
support (over Zoom).
They measured
standard tests
of cognition and function
before and after in each group,
as well as objective
experimental biomarkers
of disease progression.
On the Clinical Dementia
Rating Global scale,
which is used to stage
the severity of dementia,
the control group
continued to get worse,
but the diet and lifestyle
group started to get better.
People diagnosed with
Alzheimer’s getting better?
The same seemed to
happen when measured
with the Alzheimer’s Disease
Assessment Scale,
though this did not reach
statistical significance.
Using what’s called the
Clinical Dementia Rating
Sum of Boxes scoring,
both groups
continued to deteriorate,
but the decline was significantly
less in the healthy living group.
Overall, using
what’s called the
Clinical Global Impression
of Change scoring,
most of the people in the
control group kept getting worse
and none showed any improvement,
which is what you'd expect with Alzheimer's,
whereas about 40% of those
in the diet and lifestyle group
appeared to be getting
better within five months
of eating and
living healthier.
Why did some get
better and others not?
Well, the more they complied
with the recommendations,
the greater the beneficial impact
on their cognition and function.
This helps to
explain why studies
of less-intensive
lifestyle interventions
were not sufficient to
stop disease progression,
let alone actually improve
cognition and function.
The biggest limitation
of the study is that,
unlike drug trials where
you can give people
a disguised placebo
sugar pill,
when a study involves major
diet and lifestyle changes,
you can’t rule out
the placebo effect,
especially for self-
reported, subjective
“How’s your memory been?”
type-questions.
But the researchers
also measured
objective investigational biomarkers
of disease progression
and saw the same
trajectory—
improvements in the
interventional group
and worsening in
the control group,
with the same apparent
dose-response effect,
meaning the more they improved
their diet and lifestyle,
the more dramatic the effect.
Compare that to the
latest Alzheimer’s drugs,
which may not
even work at all.
All you may get
for your $56,000
is a one-in-three chance of
swelling or bleeding in your brain.
When the U.S. Food
and Drug Administration
approved the
drug anyway,
the head of the American
Geriatrics Society replied,
“My head just exploded.”
The bottom line is
there is only one diet
that's ever been shown to help
reverse our leading cause of death,
heart disease,
in the majority of patients:
a plant-based diet.
If that’s all a plant-
based diet could do—
reverse the number one
killer of men and women,
then shouldn’t that be the default
diet until proven otherwise?
And the fact that it
can also be so effective
in preventing, arresting,
and reversing
the progression of
other leading killers,
like high blood pressure,
type 2 diabetes,
and now maybe even early-
stage Alzheimer’s disease
would seem to make the
case for plant-based eating
simply overwhelming.
In our next story,
we look at the human impact of improving the
cognition and function of Alzheimer’s patients.
I released a video
profiling Dr. Dean Ornish’s
landmark new study
in the leading peer-reviewed
Alzheimer’s translational
research journal,
a randomized controlled trial
showing that a plant-based
diet and lifestyle program
may significantly improve
cognition and function
after 20 weeks in many patients
with early-stage Alzheimer's disease.
About 70% remained stable
or actually improved
in the plant-based
intervention group,
whereas,
in the control group,
about 70% got worse and
not a single person got better.
But no matter how
significant the results,
the dry statistics just don’t
convey the human impact.
Many patients who
experienced improvement
reported regaining cognition
and function they had lost,
but how does that actually
translate into real life?
Well, for example, several
patients in the intervention group
reported that they had been unable
to read a book or watch a movie
because they kept forgetting what
they just read or watched
and had to keep starting over,
but after the plant-based diet
and lifestyle changes,
they got better,
such that now they were able
to read and watch shows again.
One individual reported that
it used to take him weeks
to ﬁnish reading a book,
but after participating in the study,
he was able to do it
in a matter of days.
Another participant,
a former business executive,
reported regaining the ability to manage
his own ﬁnances and investments.
“It was so much
a part of my life”, he said,
“who I am, and who I was—
it was hard saying that
part of me was just gone.
But now I’m back to
reconciling our ﬁnances monthly;
I keep up to date
on our investments.
A lot of self-worth
comes back.”
Another one said that for ﬁve
years she had been unable
to prepare their family
business’s ﬁnancial reports,
but now she is able
to do so accurately.
“A deep sense of
identity is returning.
It’s given me a
new lease on life,
and yet it’s a familiarity and something
I’ve always prided myself on.
I’m coming back like I was prior to the
Alzheimer’s disease being diagnosed.
I feel like I’m me again—
an older but better version of me.”
But even words are hard to
describe such transformations.
One of Dr. Ornish’s study participants
gave us permission to share his story.
Dan Jones, a musician at
military events and parades,
who was diagnosed
with Alzheimer's disease.
"What do you notice that you could
do now that you couldn't do before?"
"Well, for one thing,
I had a set of about eight tunes
that I played in the parade.
And I could just go straight through
them from one into the other.
I played for an hour and
a half without stopping.
I think it was pretty close.
They move darn
slow in that parade.
I was leaving them
behind walking.
I kept having to stop and
wait for them to catch up."
"Was that something different?"
"Yeah."
"And what was?"
"Well, that I could
remember the order.
I could make the transition from
tune to tune without messing up
and getting confused about
which tune I was playing.
Those were all problems I'd
had when we were playing
at the graduation ceremony.
You know,
I'd forget which tune
was coming next.
I'd get worried about it,
and I'd start making mistakes.
And this just went
like clockwork.
A lot of it had to do with practice,
but the tunes we played before,
I had played hundreds of times.
And I was messing up,
and in the parade,
I hardly messed up at all."
"And you were messing up because
you had a hard time remembering?"
"Because I had a hard
time remembering.
I'd get confused
about different tunes.
It was really, yeah, it was
not a pleasant experience.
It was unpleasant enough that,
like I said,
I went home and put them down.
And now, there was one
day a couple of weeks ago
when I really had
the drones in tune.
It was in the evening,
I was out on the
front porch playing,
and it was just so beautiful.
I played for 2 hours.
I just stood there and played."
I'm crying because I'm happy.
It was just so nice to
be able to do that again."
"Did that make you feel
better about yourself too?"
"It did."
"In what way?"
"I just felt like I
could do something.
I had worth again,
so to speak.
Something that was important
to me was given back."
Here’s what the head
of Harvard’s Brain Center
at Mass General had to say:
Big Pharma has invested
billions in the effort
to ﬁnd medications
to treat the disease,
but only two Alzheimer’s drugs have
been approved in the last 20 years—
one of which was already
just pulled off the market,
and the other is minimally effective,
extremely expensive,
and often has
pesky side effects
such as brain swelling
or bleeding into the brain.
In contrast, the intensive lifestyle
changes implemented in this study
have been shown here to
improve cognition and function,
at the cost of, like,
buying broccoli,
and the only side
effects are positive ones.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you want to see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age” has
been out for about half a year now.
Check it out from your
local public library.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.